Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn Twitter/FB/IG
@BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady, do you really trust Consort Honnête?
"Only use those you trust, never the ones you suspect."
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
What brings Your Majesty here at this time?
Your Majesty surprises me.
"By the little carved window, she was combing and adorning herself."
Now I know what a peaceful and harmonious sight that is.
Why are you combing your hair at this time?
Your Majesty seemed very happy when you came in.
Will Your Majesty tell me the happy news
so I can share the feeling with you?
Huan Huan, your senses are as refined as your hair.
In court this morning,
officials reported a surplus in revenue and food supplies for this year.
The people can live a happy and stable life now.
I am very happy to hear that.
I also visited Consort Honnête yesterday night.
Consort Honnête is typically taciturn,
but she is quite reasonable when she does voice her opinion.
Consort Honnête is wise and knowledgeable
because of her long residency in the palace.
And Your Majesty has always been benevolent to all,
making wise decisions on both household and external affairs.
That's why the country enjoys prosperity and stability today.
As I witness the stability in the court,
I try to picture when Empress Première
was leading your lord concubines.
If Empress Première was still with us today,
I believe the ambiance of the harem would be much different.
You've heard accounts of Empress Première?
Jinxi entered the palace early.
She often told me how Empress Première
bestowed grace upon all the servants.
Although this may sound presumptuous,
if Empress Première was still alive,
how would Her Majesty resolve the affair
between Jinxi and Su Peisheng?
If Empress Première was still alive...
The Empress is the younger sister of Empress Première.
I assume Their Majesties shared the same disposition.
Although Her Majesty intends to use this incident
as a warning to the harem,
I suppose...
Her Majesty will not actually take their lives.
Especially given Your Majesty's benevolence,
I'm sure Her Majesty
will not act in contradiction to Your Majesty
and Empress Première's inclinations.
How can Yixiu compare to Empress Première?
I have been thinking it must be exhausting for you to carry twins.
Yet, the palace is filled with rumors that you are not carrying my children.
I don't mind what others say,
but even the Empress has also mentioned it.
Her Majesty is justly concerned about the affairs of the harem.
Consort Honnête was correct.
With two concubines pregnant,
the palace shouldn't see any bloodshed.
Even if they should be punished, it should be postponed.
Earlier, Your Majesty asked My Lady why she was combing her hair at this time.
There is a reason for it.
Jinxi's situation has upset and saddened My Lady.
It's been two days since My Lady got a decent night's sleep.
Dr. Wen suggested combing the hair
can help calm anxiety and improve sleep.
Quiet.
Who gave you permission to "chew your tongue" before His Majesty?
Your Majesty, don't listen to Jade.
I have been sleeping very well.
You still want to deceive me?
I can tell you haven't slept well by the dark circles under your eyes.
Huan Huan, you always make compromises
and even forbid Jade from telling the truth.
It's already a blessing for me to serve Your Majesty again.
It's of no concern that sometimes I need to make compromises.
But I just can't bear to see Jinxi suffer
as she has been by my side all these years.
However, I understand Jinxi is at fault here.
Her Majesty is the head of the harem.
If she wants to punish Jinxi by the palace rules,
there is nothing I can do but obey.
Though the Empress is in charge of the harem,
I can always step in.
Your Majesty must not vent anger on Her Majesty over this.
I am the only one to blame.
I failed to properly instruct my servant.
This kind of thing has happened in every dynasty.
Ever since "heaven and earth were separated,"
these relationships have existed.
They are just normal men and women with human desires.
Though eunuchs don't count as men,
they still have human affection.
I shouldn't try to extinguish their human desires.
This incident, after all, happened within these palace walls.
It's better to solve it quietly.
If we let this draw too much attention from the citizenry,
it will only give rise to ridicule.
Besides, Su Peisheng has been serving Your Majesty since your childhood.
He has spent more days and nights by Your Majesty's side
than I have.
His hard work should offset one mistake.
"Spent more days and nights by my side"?
It sounds like you are jealous of him.
It's true that "Only women and small men are hard to deal with."
I am a woman,
with small men in my belly.
If Your Majesty thinks we are hard to deal with,
then just leave us alone.
How can I bear to do that?
Jinxi!
Your Highness!
Your Highness...
- It's good that you're back.
- How is Your Highness?
Good, good to see you back.
Your Highness, please forgive me.
Rise, quickly!
His Majesty said that
your punishment is just one year's stipend.
As long as you're fine, nothing else matters.
I'm thankful for Your Highness and His Majesty's grace.
Go with Jinxi and help her get some rest.
You don't need to serve me these two days.
I'm all right, Your Highness.
How is Su Peisheng?
All is well. He's already back to work at the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Go have some rest.
I thank Your Highness.
Jade, help Jinxi get rested.
Let's go.
Su Peisheng... bows before Your Majesty.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
You are back.
I thank Your Majesty.
Even sacrificing my life would not repay Your Majesty's grace.
Good to have you back. Now grind ink.
Yes.
Your Majesty, please have some cloud ear soup first.
I will prepare your ink right away.
I know what you want to ask.
The Palace of Eternal Longevity and Cui Jinxi are both fine.
I punished you both with a fine of one year's stipend.
A small punishment to prevent you from making a bigger mistake.
I have to take the Empress's opinion into account
on this kind of inappropriate matter.
I need to demonstrate my stance.
Your Majesty, I understand.
You should have told me earlier.
I'm afraid that this kind of matter
would soil Your Majesty's ears.
Forget it. Don't stay in personal contact with her anymore.
In case there are gossips again.
Your Majesty,
Jinxi and I have known each other for a long time
and we're from the same hometown.
I'm getting old.
I've taken the cut and will never have children.
I deserve no one by my death bed.
I just want to...
have Jinxi's company.
Your Majesty...
I'm sincere.
All right.
Forget what I said just now.
Nor did I hear what you said.
Have it your own way.
I thank Your Majesty for the great grace.
I thank Your Majesty.
Peace to My Ladies.
Her Majesty just got up.
Please come back later to pay your respects.
The chrysanthemums here are in full bloom.
We'll enjoy the flowers in the courtyard
so that Her Majesty can take her time.
As you please, My Ladies.
What you said is so true.
Like master, like servant.
The whole thing caused an uproar.
I want to see how Consort Lumiere can save face.
How can she save face?
She won't find it anywhere in the harem!
If I were her, my servant and I would hide together
and never leave the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Cui Jinxi is her trusted subordinate.
Perhaps she needed that sachet to seduce His Majesty.
She just had the servant keep it for her.
Peace to Your Highness Consort Lumiere.
I haven't gotten a chance to congratulate you, Lady Delice -
you are finally released from confinement.
You must've been extremely bored when confined.
Jumping into the crowd the minute you're released.
Your Highness has eyes like mirrors to see what's right and wrong.
No need to "call a stag a horse" or "describe black as white".
Her Majesty made the request to His Majesty for you to be released
so we can reunite for the Mid-Autumn Festival.
I thought you learned your lesson,
but you're still so quick to lose your temper.
What a terrible waste of Her Majesty's good intentions!
It's my own mistake if I did something wrong,
which is nothing compared to Your Highness's servant,
who did such a shameless thing.
I wonder if it's "because the top beam is crooked, the entire house is twisted."
For the past few days, I've been sick and unable to get up.
Now that I am better, I came to serve Your Highness.
Allow me.
Jade, you should have carried a cape for Her Highness on such a cold morning.
His Majesty will worry if Her Highness gets sick.
Lady Délice, as a concubine, is it appropriate for you
to speak to Her Highness Consort Lumière in this way?
You say "The top beam is crooked, so the entire house is twisted".
But Consort Lumière ranks as Consort while you're just a Noble Lady -
at least you should know the difference between superiors and inferiors.
Moreover, when you mistreated your residents the other day,
do you also blame "an upper beam that was crooked"?
You can twist your words but they won't be the truth.
You are the one twisting the words, Cui Jinxi!
You are the one who desecrated the harem!
Yes, I'm on good terms with Su Peisheng.
Well, what of it?
Even if you don't like it,
it was His Majesty who released me.
Therefore, I do not deserve the accusation of "desecrating the harem".
If you insist on this,
are you implying that His Majesty sheltered me
and allowed me to create disorder in the palace?
So what do you all think?
Do you share the same mind as Lady Délice?
We dare not, Your Highness.
Her Majesty is ready.
My Ladies, please come in.
Ah, Jinxi is here.
Yes, Your Majesty.
It's my duty to serve Consort Lumiere.
Jinxi, you're senior in the palace.
You should serve Consort Lumiere with extra care.
Don't cause any more trouble and upset her.
Yes. I thank Your Majesty for your guidance.
The Mid-Autumn Festival is approaching.
Noble Prince Guo is coming back to the capital.
Besides, Consort Lumiere will deliver her child soon,
and Concubine Vertu is pregnant.
His Majesty wants a proper celebration.
We will be delighted to follow your arrangement.
Su Peisheng bows before Your Highness.
You're here.
His Majesty asked me to bring a serving of
red dates and hasma to nourish Your Highness's health.
I thank His Majesty.
Thank you too, sir.
Jade, grant Mr. Su a seat.
I thank Your Highness.
I haven't seen you for a few days, sir.
You have slimmed down a lot.
I thought I was pretty strong and healthy.
I didn't expect to become feeble like this
after several days of hard labor work in the Department of Penalty.
I'm indeed old and useless.
Since I'm still serving His Majesty, no one dares gossip.
But ...
How are things with Jinxi?
I'm sure your heart can see it, sir,
the reason so many people gossip about Jinxi
is that she works for me.
The incident was only because you accidentally dropped the sachet.
I endeavored to protect the two of you and I was at my wits' end.
Fortunately, His Majesty took into account your past service.
Yes.
I was careless.
I didn't expect that even Her Majesty the Empress would become involved.
I'll keep this lesson in mind.
This is not only a lesson for you, sir;
it is now in my memory as well.
Yes.
So Jinxi...?
You can rest assured.
I absolutely can, having heard Your Highness say so.
Allow me to take my leave.
Certainly.
No, you shouldn't have.
Let me do it myself. Let me do it.
Just sit.
You don't see your clothes have worn out.
Aren't you afraid of being scolded by His Majesty?
I know you're versatile,
but ...you can't attend to everything.
Are you all right?
I'm good; I'm really good.
The more miserable they think I am,
the more committed I am to living well.
I live for myself.
Am I going to hang myself to fulfill their wish?
You are right.
However, I know
you came to me back then
because you had to help Consort Lumière.
If your heart hasn't been committed,
the rumors now must be hard to bear,
we can end this now,
so you don't need to put up with all this.
What are you talking about?
We are together because we need a partner in our lives.
Besides Consort Lumière,
you are the only person connected to me.
During my days in the Department of Penalty, I also realized
it would be the most foolish and unworthy thing to do -
to hurt a person who truly cares about me -
over a few rumors.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
It's a big day for you, My Lady.
Why not wear something red to look festive?
It looks like the red cheeks of a country matchmaker.
Bring me something green.
My Lady, you wear green
or light blue every day.
Why don't you wear a different color today?
I said green, and I mean green.
If you insist on being festive,
then bring me that dress with the "coupling joy" flowers embroidered.
Yes.
My Lady.
You look good.
You will accompany me to the Mid-Autumn banquet
at the Palace of Layered Brilliance.
I just don't want to look too ugly.
I have no intention of stealing the glory from Your Highness.
You're at an age when you should dress up to look good.
There is nothing wrong with that.
I'm not dressing up for His Lordship.
My Lady, you could look even more beautiful
if you want to make an effort.
I only feel ashamed in front of him.
If I were to dress up,
it would be only for His Majesty.
His Majesty the Emperor!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
All sit.
Take your seat.
Your hands are freezing, did you catch a cold?
Recently, it has been windy and cold at night.
Where is Yunli?
I'm late, Your Majesty.
I beg Your Majesty’s pardon for my delay.
I'm already used to your late arrivals and early departures.
You insisted on going to Shengjing back then.
You look a little haggard right now.
Unfortunately, I caught a cold when I arrived in Shengjing.
I was sick for over ten days.
It was not due to traveling.
Why did no one tell me you were sick?
What exactly were those servants doing?
I didn't let them say anything.
It was just an insignificant ailment.
I'm fully recovered now.
You need a person who can take care of you in your everyday life.
Do you have anyone in mind right now?
I wouldn't be coming alone
if I had one.
Maybe all I want in my life is
"Zhuangzi's dream to become a butterfly."
Speaking of which, Yunxi is of age as well.
It is also time to search for a wife and settle down.
Please don't tease me, imperial sister-in-law.
I share my 17th brother's desire
that I have to find someone that I love.
Look, the older one doesn't set a good example.
Now Yunxi doesn't want to marry.
The Great Qing needs only our imperial brother
to "spread out the branches" for our family.
So we have more time doing nothing.
Peace to Concubine Vertu.
I haven't said congratulations to Your Highness.
I thank Your Lordship.
Peace to Consort Lumière.
The same to you Your Lordship.
Your Highness's due date is near.
How's your health?
I thank Your Lordship for caring.
Everything is going well.
Your Majesty, it's time for My Lady to take her prenatal tonic.
Go quickly.
I'll be back soon, Your Majesty.
"I pray our life be long;
A thousand miles apart, we can still share the beauty of the full moon."
[Poem from Sushi, Song Dynasty]
My Lady, are you all right?
I thought I could hold it in.
I thought I could forget about him.
I almost couldn't behave properly.
I fully understand the bitterness in the hearts of
His Lordship and you, My lady. It's just...
He must live a good life.
Your emotions are disturbed.
Let's take time to soothe your feelings.
I will accompany you for a walk.
How have you been?
I already said earlier at the banquet
that everything is fine.
That was then. Now is now.
I stayed in Shengjing for several months.
Now I'm back,
I need to hear Your Highness say you're fine from your heart,
so that I can put my mind at ease.
If Your Lordship cares too much about my well-being,
Your Lordship will be ill at ease.
Please don't exert your mind.
Jade, let's go back.
Don't leave.
Let me go.
Let go.
I always think you're not truly happy,
even with the Palace of Eternal Longevity
being as opulent as a golden house.
Whether it's house made of gold or of hay,
I chose to live in it myself.
Whether one can live comfortably depends entirely on oneself,
and not anyone else.
Even Noble Lady Paix,
despite her humble status back then,
was much more free.
Isn't it even more true for you...
You're not her.
How do you know whether she's happy?
It's not only the person themselves
that can tell if they're happy.
The moon waxes and wanes, and so does life.
Your Lordship,
please don't be sad about people who are not worthy.
If we...
cannot live our life following our hearts,
we are more pathetic than the moon.
At least the moon reaches fullness every fifteenth.
So I won't choose this hardship in the next life.
If Your Lordship and I delay any longer,
His Majesty will be alerted.
Please take good care of yourself.
You too.
To avoid suspicion, I'll go back first.
You can go in a while later.
Who's there?
What's the matter, Jade?
I just saw a silhouette passing by.
Let's go back now.
The Imperial Garden is nearby.
It's nice in the daytime,
but it feels spooky at night.
We pass by every day.
What's there to be afraid of?
Where did all those cats come from?
Protect Her Highness!
Cats... Go quickly.
Go quickly!
My Lady! Are you all right?
My Lady!
Your Highness, Your Highness!
It hurts... It hurts!
What do we do?
Push harder, Your Highness.
Push Harder!
Push Harder, Your Highness!
Try harder, Your Highness!
Push harder, Your Highness!
Your Highness, try harder!
How is Her Highness?
Is the baby out?
What do we do?
Your Highness, push harder!
Go check if the labor tonic is ready.
Remember, for Her Highness to take it,
the tonic has to be brewed thick.
Yes!
Your Highness, His Majesty has been informed.
He will soon be here.
I have to ask, Your Highness.
If by any chance something goes wrong,
do we protect Your Highness or the children?
Wen Shichu, swear on our decades of friendship...
You have to promise me...
Whatever happens,
You cannot hurt my children!
Do you hear me?!
I knew Your Highness would say this,
but I still had to ask.
Remember,
it's best if you can keep us all safe.
If not,
you have to...
save the children!
Remember?!
Otherwise, even if I get to live,
I'll do something much worse
than committing suicide!
I've said it and I mean it.
Do you hear me?!
How can Your Highness say something
so senseless at this time?
Your Highness, His Majesty is here.
Go...
Go request of His Majesty,
If something unforeseen happens,
please forget our years of affection ...
Don't hesitate in the slightest
to give me up for the children's sake.
Your Highness!
My Lady, at this critical moment,
how can you ask Jinxi to say such inauspicious words to His Majesty?
Push, Your Highness.
Your Highness, push!
Nonsense!
I have said that both Consort Lumière and the children must be safe.
Otherwise, the whole Imperial Infirmary will be buried alongside them.
I've received too much punishment from Heaven.
My children must be safe this time! Must be!
My Lady is awake!
My children... Where are my children?
Your Highness, the nursemaids are feeding them now.
They'll be back soon.
It's a boy and a girl.
Huan Huan, you brought me a dragon and a phoenix.
Has Meizhuang been here?
And where's Dr. Wen?
Concubine Vertu is pregnant, so I let her go back to rest.
Dr. Wen is still here.
He's supervising the servants brewing the tonic.
Your Majesty, Your Highness,
I heard that a “dragon and phoenix pair”
is an auspice of prosperity and peace.
We congratulate Your Majesty!
Congratulations to Your Highness!
Well said!
I reward everyone in the Palace of Eternal Longevity with half a year's stipend,
for your tireless dedication to your master.
I thank Your Majesty.
Congratulations to Your Majesty.
Congratulations to Your Highness.
Madam, you are here.
The Empress Dowager is overjoyed to hear that
Your Highness gave birth to the twins safely.
So she sent me to deliver her greetings.
Please thank Her Majesty for me, madam.
I wonder if I could be so fortunate to be the first person
to "win the top prize" of seeing the prince and the princess.
So I can report to Her Majesty later.
Jinxi, bring the children here quickly.
Her Majesty will be elated.
It would also benefit her health.
In fact, even I haven't seen them yet.
Your Highness.
The princess and the prince bid peace to Your Majesty and Your Highness.
The prince has your forehead and chin.
The princess has your brows and eyes.
They are babies,
how can one tell any resemblance?
Your Majesty is just saying that to make me happy.
The more a father looks at his children, the more he adores them.
Huan Huan, thank you.
Your Majesty, the babies are too little.
Let's have the nursemaids take them back.
Yes, yes, go ahead.
Now I've seen the twins, I can report back to Her Majesty.
Very well.
I shall take my leave.
Yes.
Huan Huan, do you know how happy I am?
You gave birth to two children at once. It is a huge contribution.
I will promote you to Noble Consort.
You will be my beloved Noble Consort.
Your Majesty, I do not deserve the title of Noble Consort.
Besides you, no one else deserves this title in my mind.
You just shuddered. Do you feel cold?
Petunia, why did you leave the door open?
Her Highness could catch a cold. Close it immediately!
Your Majesty,
the birthing madam said that there was a strong smell
of blood in the hall, and told me to keep the door open.
So I didn't close it.
You make excuses for exposing Her Highness to cold?
Slap her twenty times outside.
Yes.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Deliver my decree to the whole harem:
Consort Lumière of the Palace of Eternal Longevity
is promoted to Noble Consort Lumière.
The formal ceremony will be held on the day when the twins turn one month old.
Noble Consort Lumière will be entrusted with the authority
to assist in palace affairs after sitting the month.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Huan Huan, do you like it?
I rejoice at Your Majesty's reward.
His Majesty is listening inside.
I'll let you slap yourself.
My hand might be too heavy.
Mr. Yun, you heard that it was not my fault.
I was just following the instructions.
His Majesty took it out on you because he cherishes Her Highness.
Don't hold any grudge.
Why does His Majesty take it out on us servants
just because he cherishes Her Highness?
Mind your tongue!
It won't just be slapping yourself if His Majesty hears that.
Your Highness, I boldly request a reward.
Your Highness is favored by His Majesty and blessed by Heaven.
Any reward from Your Highness will bring me good luck.
You deserve a big reward.
It would be more appropriate if it's from His Majesty.
You two endured great hardship in the past.
Since the Noble Consort requested,
I'll grant Jinxi to be your official wife.
Treat her well.
Yes!
I thank Your Majesty.
I thank Your Majesty and Your Highness for the good graces.
I will,
I... I will treat Jinxi well!
What are you all waiting for?
- I thank Your Majesty and Your Highness!
- Go ask for drinks from them.
Your Highness!
Have a good rest.
I'll come back to see you tonight.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Consort Estime was here earlier.
Will you see her, My Lady?
I feel tired now.
Thank Consort Estime for me, and tell her
that I will invite her over after I recover.
Reply to her with what I said.
I won't see any visitors for now.
Yes.
The little princess and the little prince are identically adorable.
Your Majesty is too joyful to take your eyes off the babies.
What a joyous occasion!
I would keep looking at them until my eyes get sore.
Keep them farther from me, so that I won't pass my weak qi to them.
Noble Consort Lumière's twins were born prematurely.
You must take good care of them.
No mistake will be pardoned.
Yes.
Have you decided on their names?
The Sixth Prince is named Hongyan.
Let me look at the Sixth Prince.
Good boy.
Unlike you, he has fair and tender skin.
You had dark skin when you were born.
Noble Consort Lumière has fair skin, and so do the twins.
The princess's honorary name hasn't been determined yet.
I'll leave that up to Noble Consort Lumière.
Good. You name the prince and she names the princess.
I will name the child of Concubine Vertu once it's born.
Now that the twins have "landed on the ground",
I can finally be vindicated from the rumor.
I will impose stern punishment on whoever spreads any rumors.
I'm blessed by Heaven to come back to Si Lang's side
and give birth to our children.
There's nothing for me to complain about.
While you were cautious of your words and actions,
others suspected the children in your belly.
I must "straighten the tongues" in the harem.
Harem affairs are just the concerns of women.
Her Majesty will exercise good judgment.
Why would Your Majesty wade into the muddy water?
Others might affirm their belief that Your Majesty is partial towards me.
I am showing my partiality towards you to the whole harem.
Then they will never dare to slight you at all.
The Empress used to uphold a virtuous name.
But now her "ears have grown soft",
which might be due to her age.
"East and West are the nearest and the furthest apart;
A clear stream can be deep but look shallow."
"The sun and the moon are the highest and brightest;
Husband and wife can be closest and most distant."
As long as Si Lang has faith in me,
we will be "the closest husband and wife".
Her Majesty the Empress!
Peace to Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
Yes.
I hope Your Majesty forgives my bad manners.
Just stay there.
You have borne a great accomplishment for the entire nation.
I thank Your Majesty.
Noble Consort Lumière has given birth to two children.
I have no other gifts than these:
My sister gave me several pieces of precious
suet-white jade a long time ago.
I urged the craftsmen to work hard overnight
to carve them into a pair of jade bi for the babies as their amulets.
Her things are naturally the finest,
and suitable for the babies.
I appreciate your generosity.
My sister left me many items to remember her with.
I take them out and look at them sometimes
to remind myself of the good times we spent together.
Of course.
I haven't visited you for months.
I am old and my looks have faded.
I can't compare to the young concubines
who are healthy and able to conceive children.
Your Majesty should visit young concubines more when you have time,
instead of locking yourself all day
in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I was in the middle of sorting my sister's
belongings before I headed here this morning.
I'll take my leave while it's still well lit.
Certainly.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.